hello everyone
it is August 2nd 2023 we're in the
active inference for the social sciences
course I'm Daniel Friedman
and this is going to be a lecture on
Collective Behavior now of course
disclaimers could abound and there's so
many ways to go about this topic of
collective behavior that in actuality in
enactments I really hope it is
multi-scale and Collective I'm really
looking forward to your comments and
your engagement with this area with this
lecture with this course so if you're
watching live you can add comments into
the live chat or questions and I'll
check them out at the end
also in the YouTube live chat and in the
video description there is a link to
where you can submit questions for all
of the teachers of this course
that's going to be a coda form and just
more generally let's have fun enacting
ecosystems of shared intelligence
together and I hope that this lecture
can be something like
one attempt to make that happen
epistemically
we're gonna have many fun things to talk
about Collective Behavior what
differentiates it from Simply Behavior I
mean aren't all behaving systems
assemblages is not the brain composed of
multiple Parts brain and body multiple
people what are we really talking about
with individual Behavior why do we need
adjectives at all for Behavior what is a
collective and how would we even know it
except through its Behavior so there's
gonna be all kinds of fun topics
Avil provided me with this image and
suggested that it would be a great place
to head towards and so we can think of
this as where we're going and where
we're going is understanding the agents
or the human
in a social relationship through social
action and the recipient of social
constraints and observations
through that interface or blanket or
holographic screen the agent or the
human is engaging on this socio-cultural
landscape
and so we can think about that agents of
Engagement with the social world and the
dynamic of socio-cultural constraints
now that's where we're going and that's
how someone else has framed where we're
going
what I'll tell you here is how we're
getting there how we're getting there
it's going to be a lot of fun there's
going to be a lot of ants and the door
is going to be wide open so everyone is
an estimate on this slide and we're
going to be with our regimes of
attention and our stigmergic Trails just
absolutely up down left right all over
this socio-cultural landscape
all right
so here's the plan for the collective
Behavior lecture
it's going to be presented as a sequence
of views each view or perspective is
gonna consist of at very least a central
citation and then one or more
Reflections on that citation
or views on Collective Behavior taken as
a bundle will constitute a main section
of this lecture and there are going to
be three main sections of this lecture
split on one hand into three groups of
four and on the other hand into two
groups of six
splitting into Force the main three
sections are going to be background in
context
which is going to provide some views and
insights that are from outside of active
inference because surprise surprise what
was true before active inference or
outside of active inference is also true
within and after
then we're going to turn to active
inference specifically we're going to
talk about active inference insights and
fundamentals for Collective behavior and
applications and implications of
utilizing or of conceptualizing of a
social system as an active inference
system
so those second two sections are each
going to center around also specific
recent work in the field
to split it into two groups
of six the first six views that are
presented so all of background and
context and then half of the insights
and fundamentals are going to be in
support linguistically or rhetorically
of a declarative statement
whereas the latter six
views are going to support or open up to
a question
and that'll lead us to the final section
the fourth section which is some open
questions at that time
I will look at the live chat and review
any questions or thoughts that people
have and I'll also just open the door
and leave it open with asking questions
because that's something that we're
going to be engaged in for so so long
so let's go right into the first section
background and context
here are
the four views and the four declarative
statements
big picture many if not all of the
concepts discussions questions and views
on Collective behavior from before or
outside of active inference also apply
after or inside active inference or in
the active inference ecosystem
and so to support and to build out that
point I'm going to talk about four
different works and some takeaways first
watching behavior is complex
here we'll look at Deborah Gordon's 1992
paper wickenstein and ant watching
second all intelligence is collective
intelligence which was a presentation of
the same name by JF cloutcher earlier
this year referencing a paper of the
same name
third
we have never been individuals a work by
Gilbert at all from 2012. a symbiotic
view of life we have never been
individuals a little bit of a play on we
have never been modern
and the metaphors and Frameworks and
language that we use to talk about
Behavior to talk about Collective
Behavior what adjectives we put in front
of what nouns that matters and a great
work that Ali shared with me that I
think makes this point super well is by
Navarro and gabriellaitis from 23 and
that work is the morphology of
collective intelligence Network swarm
multitude or assemblage
so let's head straight to Professor
Gordon's 1992 work on wittenstein and
ant watching
and so
just also for a context Professor Gordon
was my PhD advisor and so I was able to
engage with this material and
perspective through asynchronous means
such as this paper but also seeing it
actually play out on a socio-cultural
landscape in the desert in southeast
Arizona
that's where the complexity really
flowered
and so
research in animal behavior Begins by
identifying what animals are doing in
the course of observation The Observer
comes to see animals as performing a
particular activity
how does this process work how can we be
certain that behavior is identified
correctly
wickenstein offers an approach to these
questions looking at the uses of
certainty
rather than attempting to find rules
that guarantee it here two stages in
research are distinguished first
watching animals and second reporting
the results to other scientists
certainty about what animals are doing
has different uses at each stage and
this is really a beautiful and subtle
point
by distinguishing
stages of the ethological encounter the
behavioral scientific encounter whether
we're talking about ants on the ground
or people in the cities
separating out the observational moments
and the uncertainties that are always at
play there
from this secondary communication about
Behavior at which point having really
clear defined articulations of behavior
becomes so important for scientific
reproducibility Integrity accessibility
and so on
personally I find that this paper
anticipates a lot of the specifications
that today we would consider part of the
metabasian perspective which is to say
we're making inferences as cognitive
systems about other cognitive systems
she wrote my questions about ant
watching do not arise when I'm watching
ants most of the time I do not think
much about certainty when ant watching
replace that for the social human
setting with people watching sometimes
we're just watching people and that's
okay that's part of the moment
I do not think much about certainty when
ant watching I enact it
the questions do not come from doubts
about the certainty of my seeing but
from the ways that doubts about the
certainty of seeing have shaped
scientific practice
the resolution of the problem would come
from changes that would allow observers
to talk about what they are actually
doing when watching animals
truthful accounts of scientific animal
watching don't yet exist
this truth is not yet formed because we
have not yet learned to talk about it
what a wonderful expression
and delightfully I came to see the
confused foragers as patrollers
searching for new food I saw the other
foragers as already decided about their
destination not available to be
distracted by a new source of food and
so we have this really fascinating
dialectic where in the moments we're
observing in this predefinitional space
not questioning though maybe we went to
the field site to ask and answer a
question get data about a question but
in the moment
we're in the flow of observation and not
asking questions though the uncertainty
may be the highest
afterwards when we're communicating to
our scientific colleagues I defined an
outgoing forager as a forger with as an
estimate with no object in the mandibles
and heading off in a straight line
passing a a demarcated point three
meters from The Colony entrance
then people why three meters why not two
meters or why can't it be carrying
something on the way out those questions
arise in that precise space of
communication
and
I wanted to open the lecture with this
view because it puts a space between I
see that person putting out a fire
they're a firefighter
in that space between
is the interpretive moment and
possibility and reimagining the social
has so much to do with this process of
let's just say ant watching
second view in this background and
context section
and here I wanted to draw from a
wonderful presentation that JF Cloutier
uh facilitator and participant at the
Active inference Institute presented as
part of his Robotics and embodied
project where yes he's building Lego
robots that do symbolic active inference
but also opening up some great
philosophical directions and ones that
have a lot of implications for how we
think about natural artificial and
synthetic intelligence
this presentation was called all
intelligence is collective intelligence
and it was based upon
the title and drawing upon
uh recent 2022 citation by Fallen days
at all
and some of these maxims or Expressions
that JF provided
I thought were so provocative
and also brought us back to that initial
question why Collective Behavior I mean
what system isn't a collective so why do
we need the adjective if we're talking
about behaving systems
what is individual Behavior individual
what oh just one bird oh just one person
okay made up of what
and so JF wrote some expressions and and
you can see from the link and look a
little more with some images and more of
what he wrote but a few of these I
thought were just excellent intelligence
is a process enacted by interacting
parts not a property of individuals
again whatever that would even mean
inaction is death
being by doing
action without prediction is reckless
no prediction without sense making
no sense made without a self versus the
world
or a self in the world
a collective is differently intelligent
than its members
maybe trivially different maybe better
in every way maybe another Direction in
every way
why do individuals participate in
collectives why are people in groups
because
sacrificing the autonomy to the
collective provides benefit
survival or even thrival benefits
that's that I to we
no making of sense without the self
acting in or on the world it's not just
some Essence that's disembodied this is
what embodiment is all about
an autonomous agent is a self-organizing
collective of parts
of a collective can themselves be
autonomous agents
collectives form to improve the chance
of survival of their members
and an agent in a collective benefits
from the intelligence of the collective
so
to me this presentation and line of
research pursued by JF and others
absolutely puts a bow on the what is an
individual what is a collective why do
we even talk about quote individuals
or quote collectives when we recognize
the multi-scale nature of complex
adaptive systems
third perspective
a symbiotic view of life we have never
been individuals this is a 2012 paper by
Gilbert Sapp and Talbert
and just to read a few aspects of what
they wrote in the abstract the notion of
the biological individual is crucial to
studies of genetics Immunology Evolution
develop anatomy and physiology
each of these biological sub-disciplines
has a specific conception of
individuality which has historically
provided conceptual context for
integrating newly acquired data
few descriptions
animals cannot be considered individuals
by anatomical or physiological criteria
because a diversity of symbians are both
present and functional in completing
metabolic pathways and serving other
physiological functions
similarly these new Studies have shown
that animal development is incomplete
without symbiance
symbians also constitute a second mode
of genetic inheritance providing
selectable genetic variation for natural
selection
which connects it to the evolutionary
concept of an individual so if we pursue
the metabolic oh it's it's all the the
metabolic networks and how they're all
connected that's the individual all
right well that includes the microbiome
and symbionts we'll know it's the
physiology and the decision making and
the neurophysiology those are also in
play with the symbiance well at least
Evolution only selects upon the germline
right well no actually there are these
multiple mechanisms of inheritance
whether they're relevant in a given
situation or not is situational but in
principle they exist and they're
increasingly coming to be recognized
additionally for the immune system
commonly described as quote self versus
non-self or self-identification or
self-other discrimination after all we
talk about Auto grafting and
allografting but of course there are
aspects of quote self or self under some
definitions like an epitope from a
protein in cartilage than an autoimmune
disorder
might Target so the immune system is
mobilized against self
under some definitions sometime and is
not mobilized against other under some
definitions sometimes like we're not
constantly mounting uh massive immune
response to our gut microbiome or skin
microbiome
recognizing the holobiant the
multicellular eukaryote plus its
colonies of persistent symbiance as a
critically important unit of anatomy
development physiology immunology and
evolution and cognition
opens up a new investigative Avenue and
conceptually challenges the ways in
which the biological sub-disciplines
have heretofore characterized living
entities here we have the cover of the
famous work Leviathan it's a large
person constituted of other people
really making the point clear but if we
zoomed in on quote an individual person
wouldn't we find something like
societies of cells
what is an individual when is an
individual what
and what's on the line
I thought those are such big questions
maybe could we connect it to a little
bit of more of a bibliographic piece of
data just to show a snapshot and to open
up this discussion to you all
about what's on the line with what's an
individual
and so what I did is I I searched for
some literature Trends on PubMed
and here is the results per 100 000
citations for Collective Behavior
and so we see Collective Behavior first
being mentioned in the 1950s at least in
this literature database and rising up
on through around 500 or 400 or 500 per
hundred thousand so a thousand out of a
hundred thousand would be one percent so
half of a percent
of all the citations on a major biolytic
literature
um database
had Collective behavior in them so
that's that's a huge amount of work and
it looks like it goes down but when you
actually look at how many citations
there are it's been about four to five
thousand Publications per year
it's just that the rest of the
literature database may be expanding at
a faster rate so thousands of paper per
year in an appreciable fraction of work
has to do with Collective behavior and
so I thought wow that that that's that's
exciting that's great well how are we
doing compared to behavior
now Collective behavior is this lower
line in red and yeah there's a blip but
behavior is up between 15 and 20 percent
of citations in PubMed
now maybe behavior is also referring to
the behavior of a given material that
may or may not be a superconductor or
might be using different understandings
of behavior
um
but what what can we say and what can we
know about the difference between
individual and Collective Behavior
now interestingly here I searched for
individual Behavior as a specific term
so we see a lot lower but individual
Behavior
I mean can the tide have already turned
can it really be the case that after
2020 this is a real meaningful decline I
don't know it's too early to say we
can't do technical analysis just like
that but very provocative and gives us
some ways to look at the broader scale
or Collective scientific cognitive
process associated with these incredibly
important philosophical and and
biological questions about individuality
because of course to distinguish
Collective behavior from Individual
Behavior or why will you why would you
even need an adjective at all it's going
to come down to what is an individual
and what's on the line so much
in the last view here
drawing upon the work morphology of
collective intelligence Network swarm
multitude or assemblage and Tony Navarro
and Alejandra Lopez gabrieladis wrote
Network swarm and multitude are some of
the different metaphors that have been
used to understand the concept of
collective intelligence all of them have
reflected our relationship with the
internet and its development
with the Advent of artificial
intelligence AI
we wonder about other metaphors that
might offer a new understanding of
collective intelligence
to address today's environmental and
socio-technical challenges
they bring up Network swarm and
multitude to advocate for the fourth
option assemblage
understanding collective intelligence as
an assemblage allows for the inclusion
of different human and technological
agents and overcomes the antipocentrism
human centrism
human exclusionism of other models based
on human will whether extended as in the
multitude or suppressed as in the Swarm
connotations here
in this way ethical decision making and
responsibility are distributed among
different cognitive actors with a
capacity to choose and interpret
and to the extent that they make
decisions albeit algorithmic ones they
are also accountable and I love this and
I think it foreshadows where we're going
to be going with active inference which
is
different cognitive actors have the
capacity to choose and interpret we
might connect that to sensory and
internal states of an active inference
agent but perception sense making signal
processing inbound information
and decision making and responsibility
and accountability
and the accountability that we associate
with human socio-technical systems
that's the action selection control
theory outgoing dependencies in the
Markov blanket so right there coming
from outside of active inference we see
the identification of the need to have
flexible Frameworks including linguistic
and metaphorical
that allow us to talk about
heterogeneous diverse cyber physical
systems where different entities are
engaged in different practices and ways
of incoming sense making and outgoing
decision making and it's going to turn
out that active inference is an
incredible and flexible expressive
framework that's going to allow us to
talk about those kinds of systems
pointed to here
and it really matters they point to some
of the most important aspects of issues
today
on to active inference insights and
fundamentals well here as in all the
other areas there are so many pieces of
literature that could have been drawn on
that's why I restricted myself to just
four views
also this section is going to Mark the
Midway point we're not there yet don't
worry but the Midway point of the
lecture where we move from the six
declarative expressions
on to the questions because it's more
open than not and there's more space for
you to respond than you may imagine
but what are the views going to be here
and what are the literature that support
that point
so first active inference in the free
energy principle which is a principle
that provides a lot of
theoretical grounding and physics-based
perspective on active inference but
we're not going to go too much into it
today
active inference in the free energy
principle are scale free formalisms for
cognitive systems
with collectives as with individuals the
general framing in itself does very
little
however with properly constructed
generative models we can get explanation
prediction design influence and
implementation tools and here I'm going
to draw on two pieces of work epistemic
communities under active inference by
Mao and colleagues in 2022 and just from
several days ago the work by Connor
Hines and colleagues collected behavior
from Surprise minimization
we'll unpack the point more when we get
there
second collectives can be understood of
consisting
as consisting of action perception Loops
which subsume in tail or supervene upon
individual level action perception loops
Niche modification
stigmergy can also be modeled this way
we'll draw upon the paper octave in
France an active inference framework for
ant colony Behavior by myself and
colleagues in 2021
and then we'll move into the questions
and things will start to open up so if
it feels like we've been climbing uphill
we're two-thirds of the way with the
uphill climb feels like we've been going
downhill
we're together just away with a downhill
how do the concepts of generalized
synchrony and homeostasis which are so
core to active inference relate to
Collective Behavior
here we'll discuss the work by RAF
Kaufman at all from 2021 an active
inference model of collective
intelligence
and lastly in this section how can
active inference be used to explore the
balance between individual and
Collective behaviors and the
bi-directional influence of collectives
on individuals and of course vice versa
here we'll draw upon the computational
boundary of a self developmental
bioelectricity drives multicellularity
and scale free cognition by Mike Levin
in 2019.
so let's get right into the work by Mal
and Connor and colleagues
first I'm just going to bring this paper
up however first
you can watch more about it in guest
stream 17.1 from March 2022 here's two
two collectives right here
and also Mao will be covering this work
in a lot more detail later on in the
course I just wanted to bring it up
because I think it's one of the
exceptional examples
that can be deployed to show like hey
just thinking about the social as an
active inference system is awesome it's
an intuition pump it brings us into the
active inference ecosystem but then what
do we do when we're there and what we do
when we're there is we develop
generative models that actually take us
towards where we want to be
again
framing a situation as being related to
active inference or you could do an
active inference model of that does very
very little work by itself however
making generative models of situations
even if they're speculative generative
models or qualitative or hypothetical
that can start getting towards doing
work but if someone said well that
health condition you could do a linear
regression
okay but which treatment do we do well
it could be done with a linear
regression we could use a linear
regression to figure out what what
method to use okay but you know more or
less hotter room or colder room well
just use a linear regression
so that's the conversation that we're
having a lot with active inference a lot
of times people are talking about
whether a given situation can or cannot
be modeled with active inference or just
in the abstract what does active
inference say about this situation and
again the framework itself is generals
the point of doing little work and we
love it that way it enables us to move
into systems of interest and deploy
generative models so what they did in
this paper was leverage the active
inference framework to provide an
in-silico model on the computer chip
model
of confirmation bias and its effect on
Echo chamber formation they had a system
of Interest people's social engagement
on so-called social media and they had
even a phenomena of Interest which was
Echo chamber formation
they built a model based on active
inference where agents tend to sample
information in order to justify their
own view of reality something we call
self-evidising
we show that once agents have reached a
certain level of certainty about their
beliefs it becomes very difficult to get
them to change their views
the system of self-confirming beliefs is
upheld and reinforced by the evolving
relationship between an agent's beliefs
and observations
which will over time will continue to
provide evidence for their ingrained
ideas about the world
well where I'm from we drive on the
right side of the road and so you drive
on the right side of the road I drive on
the right side of the road we're not
going to have an issue everywhere I look
I see cars moving around I see people
passing on the right on the sidewalk
it's all making sense we're bounding
surprise we're doing active inference
surprisal minimization goals reward
never need to come into play to give an
account of how those systems could arise
and be stabilized
these epistemic communities are
Consolidated by those shared beliefs and
in turn tend to produce perceptions of
reality that reinforce those shared
beliefs and on the top right is just a
little teaser of what a Bayesian
graphical model looks like of the kind
that they deployed in this paper
and here we see some of the results from
their parameter sweeping exploring
different combinations of parameters and
looking at topics like polarization
index and re-attendance rate
and so all kinds of Statistics that can
be drawn upon connected to the
generative model and also all kinds of
opportunities and interfaces to relate
this to empirical data
as well as suggested experiments so Mal
is going to talk more about this and
it's awesome work and then late breaking
news
only several days ago five or so days
ago
an amazing new preprint was put up by
Connor Hines and colleagues and it was
just too cool not to include here and
reflects the very rapid pace of
collaborative development in the active
inference ecosystem and this is their
work Collective behavior from Surprise
minimization
and they made every point I wanted to
make Here and Now
Collective motion is ubiquitous in
nature
typically such macroscopic patterns
arise from decentralized local
interactions among constituent
components
EG individual fish in a school
there's that word individual again
preeminent models of this process
describe individuals as self-propelled
particles subject to self-generated
motion and social forces such as
short-range repulsion and long-range
attraction or alignment hmm
however organisms are not particles
they are probabilistic decision makers
they're cognitive particles
we introduce an approach to modeling
Collective Behavior based on active
inference
this cognitive framework casts Behavior
as the consequence of a single
imperative to minimize surprise
again if you want to you can contrast
that with reward learning where the
imperative is to maximize reward
inactive inference and the free energy
principle we're taking a path of least
action not the laziest path or the most
passive one but a little bit more
technically a path of least action
and we're minimizing surprise we're
bounding surprise with variational free
energy and it turns out that that helps
us minimize surprise and maximize model
evidence and it can include things like
novelty and curiosity seeking very
naturally so this doesn't mean we're
squeezing the juice out of life at all
we demonstrate that many empirically
observed Collective phenomena including
cohesion milling and directed motion
emerge naturally when considering
Behavior as driven by active Bayesian
inference without explicitly building
behavioral rules or goals into
individual agents
no reward no goal
no master of the collective
furthermore we show that active
inference can recover and generalize the
classical notion of social forces as
agents attempt to suppress prediction
errors that conflict with their
expectations
by exploring the parameter space of the
belief-based model we reveal non-trivial
relationships between the individual
beliefs and group properties like
polarization
and the tendency to visit different
Collective States
we also explore
how individual beliefs about uncertainty
metacognition beliefs about beliefs
determine Collective decision-making
accuracy
what if when you voted or shared your
perspective on what we were going to
have for dinner you also conveyed an
uncertainty estimate how confident are
you about that being the case
finally we show how agents can update
their generative model over time
resulting in groups that are
collectively more sensitive to external
fluctuations and encode information more
robustly
from a distributed systems perspective
you can imagine two different kinds of
distributed systems or networks one of
them has a dampening like quality so
something that enters on one side
dampens as it diffuses
we can also contrast that with another
kind of distributed system or another
kind of input or stimulus or context
that amplifies and the goal or one nice
property to have a systems would be like
we want to dampen what we don't want to
pay attention to and
up signal or increase the cascading
availability of what we do want to
attend to now that's a little circular
since in some ways that's the definition
of attention however making unified
models like they do here gives us
integrated approaches to explore a broad
range of collective phenomena here in
spatial movement but also involving the
cognitive states of the particles and
they make a really nice representation
here to connect to other approaches
a traditional approach to classical
self-propelled particles is Agent
environment agents take rules
and they make decisions based upon those
rules that are either given or learned
you know when you're this close to the
bird next to you do that and when you're
this close do this and then social
forces of these kind of as if or actual
constraints that then modify the agent's
perspective and what we see in the
active inference setting is that the
agent in the environment are mediated by
an interface
the Markov blanket this is the sensorium
this is on the inbound side perception
and on the outbound side action
and they give some more details it's a
really exciting paper and it's just cool
to see again that even in the the
Preparatory days of a lecture like this
like there's always new Collective
activity in the ecosystem and that's
what makes it fun
last of the declarative sections of this
lecture
colonies
here but more generally collectives can
be understood as consisting of action
perception Loops which subsume in tail
or supervene upon individual level
action perception loops
Niche modifications or stigmergy can
also be modeled this way
what we did in this paper was
bring something new to active inference
in at least two different ways
first it was the it was the first model
of an ant's system of Interest now for
some of us mere mycologists in the
audience all of our broader entomology
colleagues that may be enough but what
was also really interesting about this
work and the opportunity to collaborate
on it was it was the first active
inference model presented with explicit
stigmergy not just the philosophical
consideration of the traces that agents
leaving in the environment might then
um have them change their behavior in
the future but but explicitly engaging
with this process of multi-agent
stigmergic behavior
active inference may be informative in
the study of ant colonies at three
distinct temporal scales nestmate
Behavior which is to say emergent among
tissues of anesthemate
you could keep on going collectively
down
and interactions with the biotic or
abiotic environment so first level at
the level of an estimate one of those
things with six legs that looks like an
insect
at the level of the colony
Colony development is emergence among
nestmates and their interactions with
the niche that is where many people
would traditionally assign Collective
Behavior they said well well one
estimate walking around is individual
Behavior that's the individual ants and
then the colony is where Collective
Behavior comes into play right and we're
going to see that reified very soon
but lastly we point to the evolution of
populations which is an emergent outcome
amongst colonies within an ecology
in this work we focused on the
connection between the first two levels
of analysis
focusing on the case of stigmergic
colony foraging using a modification of
previous active inference computational
implementations
we didn't use the word individual and
there's a reason why because
we're saying what we mean more clearly
when talking about ants when we talk
about Nest mates colonies and
populations of colonies
that side steps or transcends the
discussion of what is an individual and
what is a collective because with
respect to the Colony as an individual
if you want to use that word the
population is a collective with respect
to the nest main the colony is a
collective with respect to the tissue
like the brain or the mid gut the
nestomy is a collective so we don't need
to play the adjective game we can just
articulate what we're interested in
about these systems of interest and
complex adaptive system phenomena
and so what we did was we explored a
kind of classical behavioral setting
which is food being placed between the
arms of a teammates and in this case
rather than a rat
I'm just pausing for a second while I
believe that my
internet is reconnecting and we should
be back
each ant
was described by an action perception
Loop an active inference action
perception Loop and they were able to
move within a three by three grid
as well as perceive pheromone density
within a three by three grid and then
they laid down pheromone they added
stigmergic trace on the way home if they
had found a seed and so this does a few
interesting things and and live stream
29 is where we unpack this a lot more
but I just wanted to make two more
points here the first is that in a
reward Centric perspective on AMP
Behavior
the pheromone is seen as a semiotic cue
and the seed or the food is seen as the
reward and so then we got to use the
cues we've got to use the pheromone
density to like figure out where the
good stuff is that's that paradigm
we flipped that with active inference
now the preference we don't need to say
reward but the preference that which is
sought after
proximally but teleologically
that which is sought after preferred
over is the pheromone
the seed becomes the semiotic cue that
it's time to turn on your pheromone
depositing and come home
and so that blips our approach to
understanding what foraging is about
from we're lost in the sauce trying to
figure out where the good thing is out
there to we're surfing the hundred foot
wave
and we'll know it when we see it and
then we'll turn around
very different perspective and then one
other point that I had to make for the
context was that we used a modification
of a previous active inference
computational implementation what was
the the paper that we drew from
in fact it was the acquisition of
culturally patterned attention Styles
under active inference with Axel and
Alex at all
and what this paper did
was they looked at the situation of
visual foraging
on avas a piece of pottery
where the eye was only able to perceive
a three by three Matrix of pixels
and then the I scanned around looking to
recognize broader patterns that were
then culturally acquired so maybe one
culture or one subculture likes the
checkerboard pattern and another one
likes vertical lines another one likes
horizontal lines or these other kinds of
repetitive structures
what's so interesting is that the I when
it is foraging
does not leave a trace though it can
feel like it doesn't it but the eye
Forge is around
in order to get the bigger picture
based on local information
what we did is we said well instead of
imagining that as the Gaze location of
an eye
let's imagine that as the skin in the
game exoskeleton on the ground of a
forager
so let's think about that movement
as something that an embodied forager
does with its real body
and then conditional in this setting
upon it touching the seed or the food it
can lay down a pheromone Trail which the
eyes can't do per se
and so just really interesting because
it's not like this was an ant paper and
now we're going to try to cram it into
social sciences it's actually like
computational work in the social
sciences
was able to translate to miracology into
ants research
and so it's a very fruitful and
bi-directional relationship between
studying ants and studying people
now we're going to move into the
openness of questions in this second
half of the lecture
so how do the concepts of generalized
synchrony and homeostasis which are core
to active inference relate to Collective
Behavior
and here we can draw upon the work by
RAF Kaufman pranav Gupta and Jacob
Taylor from 2021 called inactive
inference model of collective
intelligence and this was also unpacked
in guest stream nine and so here's a
little Collective over here and that was
about two years ago
way back when
what they did in this paper was they
considered a setting with two trolley
cars
moving around a wheel
and so here's how they contextualize
that work
formal models of collective intelligence
have lacked a plausible mathematical
description of the relationship between
local scale interactions between
autonomous subsystem components
individuals
and global scale behavior of the
composite system the collective
so they do a really great job faking out
what they mean by individual and
Collective
in this paper we use the active
inference formulation aif
a framework for explaining the behavior
of any non-equilibrium steady-state
system at any scale to posit a minimal
agent-based model that simulates the
relationship between local individual
level interaction and collective
intelligence
then they had a really creative approach
to disentangling how different
capacities
translated to different Collective
outcomes and here's what they did
we explore the effects of providing
Baseline active inference agents model 1
with specific cognitive capabilities
model 2 added in a theory of Minds
model 3 added in goal alignment
and model 4 added both theory of mind
and goal alignment
what does that look like again we're not
going to go into all the technical
details here but broadly this is what it
looked like here was their simplest
Baseline active inference formulation
case
and then in the subsequent experiments
they added in either one or the other or
both of the cognitive capacities that
they described
they studied the single
dyad case and they very cleverly
expanded that into a large scale
multi-diad case
they
utilized their own representation of the
active inference partition
in order to facilitate the construction
of this model and so in this case we see
the blanket with the sensory States
coming in the active States going out
Markov blanket
here we see the environment
and then internal belief States or
cognitive States
so
very cool work
that helps us
get a vocabulary around not shut the
book on
but focus on
how how do different Agents come to
synchronize what is generalized
synchrony well it doesn't mean lockstep
turn taking is generalized synchron
because these two agents the time that
they're talking has very high Mutual
information on the other
even though the correlation with their
speaking might be negative
agent a is speaking when B is not and
vice versa so from a linear regression
perspective there's a negative
correlation but from a mutual
information perspective where you can't
ever have below zero information at
worst it's just noise
you always have zero or positive amount
of information of systems about other
systems and so that opens the door to
understanding generalized synchrony
which is a broader conception of how
individuals in collectives
are interacting
and homeostasis maybe we could even
imagine that these are multiple cells in
the pancreas and they're trying to
coordinate on insulin sensitivity or
maybe this is multiple people who are
securing the defense of a community and
they also need to coordinate
synchronously and asynchronously and so
there's a lot of ways in which this very
very lightweight apparatus of the active
inference partition
helps us bring together and compose all
these cool what-ifs well what if it had
theory of mind what if it had goal
alignment what if agents had theory of
mind and goal alignment and what if we
put them in a in a five by seven grid
and then we did this and and and ants
that's what we get to do with active
inference
and lastly here
how can active inference be used to
explore the balance between individual
and Collective Behavior and the
bi-directional influence of collectives
on individuals
and so here I draw upon the amazing and
singular work of Professor Mike Levin
who wrote the computational boundary of
a self developmental bioelectricity
drives multicellularity and scale-free
cognition in 2019 this was also explored
in live stream 25 series
so just to pull out a few of the great
pieces of this article and there's a
stigmerging trail of many other papers
for those who follow
Professor Levin writes I propose a
definition of an individual
based on its information processing
structure
the scale and types of goals that A
system can pursue defines or determines
the boundaries and the content of the
putative agents
on this view what defines a coherent
unified self out of its constituents
components and the surrounding
environment is the set of parts that
operate towards reaching specific goal
States
so this is a teleological or a
functional or anticipatory or sentient
or adaptive or informational concept on
individuality
which we can add to the earlier
consideration
raised by Gilbert at all
here they discuss some of the more
mechanistic biological considerations
like genetics Immunology Evolution
development anatomy and physiology
what Levin has done here
and consistent with this is the the
informational theory of individuality by
David krakauer at all
is connect this more generally
to system capacity and so there is what
is uh here represented as like a Time
diamond
where the scope or the scale of the
system in the now is like the radius or
the circumference on this diamond
and then the part of the diamond that
recedes off into the past that's
retained from the past is memory and
history
and the part that advances or protends
into the future is the anticipatory or
the planning capacity
this opens the door to describing
diverse intelligences
including possible alien artificial
intelligence or synthetic intelligences
as well as nested or compound
intelligences so here the example is the
ant colony
so here we have cells these little
um pinkish
diamonds nested Within
a nest mate
which is the green diamond
nested within the colony which is the
Blue Diamond now notice that the
nestomate is called an organism
couldn't help but to connect this to
Wheeler 1911 whose work is the ant
colony as an organism superorganism came
later the super organismal framing on
the ant colony
reifies the concept that the nestme is
the individual or the organism
because why else would you need to call
the colony a super organism I mean I
think colonies are super I think it's
great to call them whatever you want to
call them and they probably don't mind
either but the idea that a super
organism is composed of other organisms
means that the nestomate is an organism
whereas this diagram in my perspective
would be as accurate or more to say
nestmate here because under different
concepts of organismality which is to
say individuality if we want to connect
it there
The Colony can be considered as the
organism
and of the so many other pieces of this
work that are fun to to bring out the
way that Levin clarifies his assumptions
gives us first off some planks that we
can jump off of
for good
and helps us come to terms with maybe
like how do we what do we assume about
Behavior about Collective Behavior how
do we want to show up when we're
studying Collective behavior in general
and when we're studying social behavior
after all we're in active inference for
the social sciences
and so Leven writes the ideas are
explored here from the perspective of
the following Three core assumptions
first is a commitment to Evolution every
capacity has a natural history and
emerged from simpler variants
second it is assumed that all metaphors
are to be judged by their utility in
driving scientific progress
there is not a binary categorization of
scientific pictures which should be
taken literally or not which can be
decided a priori up front
third much of the discussion centers
around goals related to teleology a
hotly debated topic here goal directness
is taken in the non-magical cybernetic
engineering and control theory sense of
a feedback system that operates to
maximize some specific State of Affairs
which can be modeled as a dynamical
system with attractors in its state
space and later work by 11 and Fields
and others expanded this concept of
intelligence just to phenomenal Heights
and flavors so
active inference helps us understand
that cognitive glue
maybe it's mechanistically enacted by
bioelectricity in a given system or at a
given scale but active inference gives
us the analytical glue to approach those
systems with an open mind
and an open scaffold
and so those are some of the insights
and fundamentals of active inference as
applied to Collective Behavioral Systems
now on to the last third of this lecture
applications and implications of active
inference for the social sciences
regarding Collective Behavior
this is really where it is wide wide
wide open
what kinds of insights can active
inference offer about the role of
learning adaptation conflict and
cooperation in Collective behavior and
how can we approach that from a
cognitive security perspective
here we'll draw on the work of Scott
David and colleagues active inference
and modeling conflict
what implications does active inference
have on the study of human Collective
Behavior particularly in social economic
and digital contexts
here we'll draw on the work by Poirier
at all
communication as socially extended
active inference an ecological approach
to communicative Behavior live stream 48
series
what considerations that are relevant
for thinking about assemblages
and interactions
what what considerations are relevant
for thinking about assemblages and
interactions among different entities in
cognitive ecosystems
here we'll turn to the work of friston
at all at all 2022.
designing ecosystems of intelligence
from first principles
and how does active inference
accommodate Collective Behavior within
and across generations and here we'll
look at a variational synthesis of
evolutionary and developmental Dynamics
by friction at all in 2023.
so when it comes to applications and
implications of active inference in
Social sitting sittings and settings
again there's so much to do there's so
much to learn so we welcome everybody
who's curious this is the time to write
your live chats submit your questions
prepare yourself to explore and to be an
active forager in this space and if
you're listening you know that you
already are
so in the work active inference in
modeling conflict
Scott David r j corday and myself asked
what kinds of insights can active
inference offer about the role of
learning adaptation conflict and
cooperation in Collective Behavior now
as with all these other papers there's
always so many things that can be said
what we did is we tried to connect
beyond the very classical Markov blanket
and agent environment partitioning which
we've seen many many times we tried to
connect this to the specific kind of
generative models that we use in
modeling so here we LED early by
clarifying this is what we're talking
about with active inference generative
models it's not like something I'm
hiding in my pocket and maybe I'll show
you if you say the shibboleth this is
what we're talking about when we're
talking about applying active inference
models to social settings it's a
discrete time generative model here
just a motif
we applied that kind of generative model
architecture
to one of the most well-known models of
sense making and decision making which
is the UDA Loop observe Orient aside act
by Jon Voight now this may seem to sound
like a quite sparse framework like yeah
you get the observation you figure it
out you make a decision you take the
action
it doesn't do that more much work by
itself either however UDA is used in
tactical and strategic settings every
single day and so we wanted to connect
UDA Loop
to the generative models that we use in
active inference and so we highlighted
on the generative model
where different stages of the ooda loop
occur perception happens in the sensory
States cognition or the the orientation
happens
in the perceptual inference the
downstairs of that part of the figure
and then decision making happens in the
upstairs with the expected free energy
calculation in this case and finally
action is selected and enacted and that
results in impact and the cycle begins
again now in active inference it's more
like an unfolding flow but to a first
pass approximation it does the trick
what does that really matter that we
understand the mechanics of decision
making well we're talking about active
inference in the social setting
that means we're talking about two
sophisticated cognitive entities maybe
two businesses maybe two individual
humans maybe a person and a business
maybe different kinds of systems that we
don't even know about or we haven't even
seen yet
and that generative model
is the internal States
that is then participating in this
minimal dyadic Collective behavioral
encounter
we can expand that to thinking about
comments resource Commons attention
Commons
open source ecosystems
and for this we utilized one of Scott
David's favorite acronyms of which he
has so so many which is bolts business
operation legal Technical and social
bolts is not an exhaustive acronym
otherwise we would need everything
but it's a heuristic that encourages us
to think holistically about different
systems let's just say that we were a
business or a person and we wanted to
see if a given policy was a good way to
go to complete our mission
and
it looks good except it can't be done
operationally well then that has to be
taken into account or everything works
out but it's illegal that's not the way
to go everything works out but the
business doesn't check out it's not
going to be sustainable financially
or technically it can't be done or
socially it's not palatable
all these features of socio-technical
systems which again we just make a
little mnemonic of with bolts need to be
taken into account for comprehensive and
high integrity High reliability systems
design
in this setting we have entity a and
entity B interacting through the bolts
Niche they each have their own blanket
States sense in action
and the niche where those Nest mates
were laying their pheromones
the niche is bolts and so you can make a
restricted model where it's just two
entities engaged in a financial dealing
just a business only engaging on B
or you could think of this multi-domain
full spectrum situation in terms of
bolts
then you would have a larger and a more
complex interface between these two
entities
but we also wanted to think about the
case where there might be cooperation
between these entities or there might be
conflict and so here we have entity A
and B the diad is in the spotlight
entity C is a non-belligerent state or
is a bystander or it's a witness or it's
a referee or it's a friend or it's a
colleague but entity C is also engaging
only through their blanket States
on bolts
and lastly we connect it to the abiotic
Niche which may not care how much you're
buying or selling a gallon of oil for
the abiotic Niche may have its own
Dynamics we may use active inference to
model that or we might use some other
approach to model it and so this sets a
really really General State space for us
to understand conflict and cooperation
and where we situated that work lastly
here
was in relationship to other work
exploring strategic and tactical
decision making and so on the lower end
of this image are tactical and
operational Frameworks that are used in
decision making on the top are strategic
or scholarly Frameworks that are used
for more of like geopolitical
considerations and then from left to
right we have more qualitative
approaches going to more formal and
quantitative approaches and we believe
that the application of active inference
through this type of model the octave
inference conflict model
helps us touch the qualitative natural
language and graphical composable
aspects and the quantitative and formal
aspects as well and similarly through
nested decision-making Cycles we can
talk about tactical operational
activities and the broader nested
strategy just like we looked at the
nested cones from Professor Levin's work
next what implications does active
inference have on the study of human
Collective Behavior particularly in
social economic and digital contexts
well there's a lot to say about this but
Tucson and Poirier wrote in 2021 the
paper communication as socially extended
active inference an ecological approach
to communicative behavior and this was
in the live stream 48 series here's Remy
raising his hands so that we knew that
he wanted to speak
they introduced an ecological account of
communication According to which acts of
communication are active inference
achieved by affecting the behavior of a
Target organism via the modification of
its field of affordances
constraining a Target organism's
Behavior constitutes a mechanism of
socially extended active inference
allowing
organisms to proactively
regulate their interstates through the
behavior of other organisms
in this General conception of
communication the type of Cooperative
communication characteristic of human
communicative interaction is a way of
constraining interaction Dynamics
towards the goals of a given joint
action by constructing and altering
shared fields of affordances
this account Embraces a pragmatist view
According to which communication is a
form of action aiming to influence the
behavior of a Target and stands against
the traditional transmission view
According to which communication
fundamentally serves to convey
information
understanding acts of communication as
active inference under an ecological
interpretation
allows us to link communicative and
ultimately linguistic Behavior to the
biological imperative of minimizing free
energy and to emphasize the
action-oriented nature of communicative
interaction this is really a rich and
excellent work that Remy and Pierre
produced
and there are several pieces that that I
think add a lot of meaning and value to
the ways that we think about
communication but most broadly what is
communication for
who do we talk to and why what do we
like to talk about and why
why would anyone say that and why
how does technique
considered broadly technology and
technique
whether it's digital or social or
cultural technique
mediate and influence communication
the media is the message the medium is
the message
and think about everything in that area
too and how can active inference Beyond
just giving these incredible composable
formal tools
how can we think about
joint action and
co-modification of fields of affordances
could you could you pick that up from
from that shelf okay I'll open it for
you now let's hand it to our friend
who's going to make the food
all of these ways in which individuals
shape each other's field of affordances
is something that we can talk about
really fluidly within active inference
penultimate View
what considerations are relevant for
thinking about assemblages and
interactions among different entities in
cognitive ecosystems
so here was a a large multi-authored
paper from Carl friston at all and the
versus colleagues designing ecosystems
of intelligence from first principles
from December 2022.
and the big picture as I see it here is
what is the role of the social sciences
after all the course that we're in now
in ecosystems of diverse heterogeneous
synthetic intelligences by synthetic
intelligences I refer to assemblages
with intelligence whether it's natural
or artificial leave that debate for
another day
because in their application we're
talking about synthetic intelligence
synthetic intelligence needs cognitive
security cognitive security needs
cognitive science
and they began this paper with the
following this white paper presents
active inference as an approach to
research and development in the field of
artificial intelligence AI artificial
with the aim of developing ecosystems of
natural and artificial intelligences
the path forward in AI is often
presented as progressing from systems
that are able to solve problems within
one narrow domain
artificial narrow intelligence a-n-i to
systems that are able to solve problems
in a domain General manner at or Beyond
human levels What are known as
artificial general intelligence AGI and
artificial super intelligence ASI
we believe that approaching ASI
or for reasons outlined below even AGI
likely requires an understanding of
networked or collective intelligence
now intelligence in action is behavior
so we're talking about Collective
Behavior
and they laid out their timeline and the
stages that they see in terms of
sentient sophisticated sympathetic and
finally shared intelligences but I think
it's worth to dwell a moment on the one
figure of this paper
one belief updating on a statistical
manifold
and so here we have some curve in an
information geometric space
it's a parameter space of a probability
distribution
and on this manifold on this line on a
plane lower dimensional manifold
projection
there's
a temporal process belief at time t t
plus one t plus two where initially this
gaussian that's very distributed
becomes updated to a sharper Peak
distribution that's going to be resting
basically at some special point on this
curve
whether you're very familiar with
accelerated optimization on information
geometric manifolds or not
it's really interesting to consider why
they went with this image and for those
again who are familiar or just coming to
be familiar with some of the formalisms
of active inference
this is what this very talented and
transdisciplinary team
went with
when seeking to provide some of the only
non-textual descriptions of their work
so I think it's really interesting and
the big question is well what is the
social
reassembling the social Bruno LaTour
what is the social what is social
does social mean only adult humans
talking with each other
does social include non-human species
does social include
non-biological intelligences these are
all things that are not just questions
of theory
and so connecting flexible extensible
Frameworks like active inference and all
that comes along with it
to this bigger question about
applications and implications
of Applied active inference in the
social setting that's what I hope we can
explore in the questions at the end of
this live stream and in the discussions
that we have in a couple of weeks and
ongoing
and lastly how does active inference
accommodate Collective Behavior within
and across generations and so here I'll
draw on the recent work of variational
synthesis of evolutionary and
developmental Dynamics with Carl friston
myself and others
and we had two
images in this work which otherwise had
a lot of prose and formalism
on the left we see that active inference
particular partition
external States internal States blanket
States
here at the organismal level
one worm
and in an enested deeper system the
population which gives rise
to the starting positionality of the
organisms think about drawing an
organism from a gene pool from a birth
pool
and the impact that those organisms have
on the bigger picture maybe it's a
bacteria that
is fermenting so it changes the pH or
the ethanol concentration of the
kombucha that is this kind of
multi-scale interaction
that we believe provides an approach to
understanding eco-evo Devo
ecology Evolution and developmental
interactions
and the other visualization that we use
here
is of nested systems so contrast that
with the kind of
time Diamond that we saw from Mike Levin
now here imagine that we're going to cut
across
the sensor of this diamond
and now it's going to look like a muscle
fiber fibers of fibers because we have
let's just say this outer Blue Line
maybe the um
The Colony
and then each of these smaller
entities is an S mate and they're
composed of cells and cells have
constituents too
and here we utilized the apparatus of
the renormalization group which draws
upon physics to articulate the
separation of scales
so that we can be clear when are we
talking about multi-scale systems which
we can articulate and renormalize across
vertically
to use an encultured metaphor and then
within a given scale of analysis what is
the lateral or Collective Behavior so
how do we get those interactions amongst
Nest mates that are both constrained by
The Colony top down again using a
spatial and uncultured metaphor top down
scaffolded or enabled or constrained by
The Colony but then what Nest mates do
matters and that influences The Colony
and we used a few new pieces of
formalism primarily developed by Carl to
help Express that setting and again we
think it's going to be really useful for
describing
otherwise quite challenging scenarios in
ecology Evolution and development
and so we come right back to that what
is a self what about nested selves
and with that I turn to some open
questions
what can be said other than
there are so many open questions to
discuss
there's
many things we can explore
in the discussion that I'll be
facilitating in a couple weeks and of
course Beyond
we have a coda interface for you to
submit questions that all the course
teachers will take a look at and give
their best attempt on
and
conversation is collective Behavior now
sure keeping it inside of your head is
also Collective Behavior
no matter how you think about it but
when we enact in the social
then
we're really making it happen
so with that I'll just show my citations
and the slides will be shared too also
there's some extra readings that various
individuals along the way suggested to
me so that includes um social ecology is
an abductive logic and acting like a
state
these are not the titles the titles are
inactive Dynamic social cognition and
active inference that was live stream
47. thinking like a state embodied
intelligence in the Deep history of our
Collective Minds that was live stream
33.
active inference applicability to
different kinds of social organizations
explained through reference to
industrial engineering and quality
management that was live stream 27.
resonating Minds emergent collaboration
through hierarchical active inference
yellow bromberg's and Eric greatville's
work on self-organization free energy
minimization and optimal grip on a field
of affordances and the well-known
thinking through other minds work by
vessier at all thinking through other
Minds a variational approach to
cognition and culture
well
I hope this has been a interesting and
relevant lecture for you
it was fun to prepare there are so many
perspectives and so much territory
that
there's a lot
in Collective Behavior but again I'm
just really looking forward to the
discussion that we can have in a couple
of weeks I encourage you whether you're
listening on your timeline
add a moment that enables you to join
that live conversation I would encourage
you to join or to join the live stream
so you can participate through through
chat or whether you want to find some
other way to get involved
it's been a great time and with that I
will close
thank you very much until next time